the teleprompter.
Data 5300 students.
Over the past few modules, you know Darth
Vader has been part of the online videos.
Some of you thought this was the
real Darth Vader. It was not.
It was just me, a professor
in a Halloween costume,
trying to make the online environment
a little more entertaining.
Also, there is no evidence
that Luke Skywalker has
been trained in SQL. He has
only been trained in the
Force. The only real cast
member, to our knowledge,
is the Stormtrooper. Thank you
for your attention to this matter.
Welcome back to Module 9.
Congratulations making it this far.
After seeing all the Darth Vader
introductions, you probably feel
like these case expressions are going
to pack your bags and go on a well
-deserved vacation. For those of you
still here, today we'll cover views
and case expressions. We're going
to break this down into three
different videos. The first video will
be on views, the second video will
be on case expressions, and then we
have a third video related to case
expressions where there's a challenge
question posed to you, and that
challenge question will specifically
be on the exam. So you certainly
won't want to miss the third video.
Let's take a look at the
deliverables for this week.
If you're on campus today, we
cover the blue triad, meaning
just taking notes on the videos
that we have. For this video,
you could take notes on the
two, the views, and the case
expressions, or you could take
notes on all three views, case
expressions, and the challenge
question, but that's up to you.
And then for the on-campus
class, on Thursday, we'll do
lab five, and for online
class, it's your schedule, so
second half of the week, you'll
probably work on lab five.
A view is a reusable type
of table expression because
their definitions are
stored in database objects.
In SQL Server, we'll have a separate
folder. You have one folder for
your tables. You'll now have a separate
folder for your views, and when
we write the code for views, those
views will show up here, and they
work just like tables. You'll
refer to them just like tables, so
instead of select star from class,
you could indicate select star from
whatever the name of this view is.
All right, let's take a look at some
of the benefits of views. The first
thing is it's a virtual table.
So when you create a view, it doesn't
physically store like a table. It
draws the data out of a table, but
you don't have data physically stored
in two places. So it's a virtual
table. And the primary benefit is
you can hide columns, rows, you can
hide names of columns, you can reuse
complex code. So you could write
some complex code, save it as a view
or in the form of a view. And then
when you refer to that view, the
complex code is already written, and
you can also add some security features.
There are some rules associated
with views. You can read in the Ben
Gaughan book about this, but you
don't use the order by in the view.
You can use the order by
outside of the view when you're
referring to it, but not when
you create it. All columns must
have names, and all columns
must be unique, and these follow
the idea of relational
mathematics, relational algebra.
And on the bottom left of the
screen, I just have an example of the
most simple view, like that prototype
example, a simple view. So you
have create, space, view, and then
the name of the view. Now the name
of the view here, I always put a V
in front of it, so V first, and then
the word as. Once you write the
word as, everything below it to the
semicolon will be contained in the
view. So if we ran this code, it
would say command successful, you
wouldn't see anything happen. But
then if we go look under views, we
would find that our first view was
created so let's go ahead and do
that you could pause the screen if
you need to to copy this code if you
want to follow along on this very
first one or you could wait to the
blue triads but I'm going to copy
and paste this information B first
there's the syntax I'm using the
university data set I run this it
doesn't show any output it doesn't
show anything under views too unless
if I click the refresh button oh
Oh, that darn refresh button.
The refresh, and here we have dbo
.vFirst. Now, dbo we'll get to later
and primarily in the advanced class.
It just represents database owner.
It's kind of a prefix to
the name of the table. So in
some coding challenges in SQL,
you actually have to write
the entire name. In this
case, it would be dbo.vFirst.
Everything I think we do
in 5300, you can just write
the name of the table or
just the name of the view.
All right, in order to
see this first one, and
we kind of know what
the code is, right? So,
in fact, before you create a
view, it's good to run that code
just to make sure it works.
I don't include the order by.
And then I can go in and run this.
In this case, I'm
selecting everything, but
instead of from student,
I'll say from vFirst,
our first use of a view. And
you can also drop a view.
just like a table. So drop
the view instead of a table
and then the name of it.
And now this view is gone. Goodbye.
Here are some examples in terms of
security. Human resources, they can
see employees' names, but not their
salaries. So perhaps some in HR
have access to everything, but others,
you don't want them to have access
to salaries, so you can create a
view. For instance, as an airline,
when you're making a reservation,
most of those people only have access
to views, they don't have access
to the underlying table, so they're
likely using views. A sales rep can
only see customers in their region,
not customers in other region, so
they can't go try steal customers.
Interns can have limited access to
the views, but not to the raw tables,
and analysts can use views without
touching production tables.
Now, in data analytics, the
primary use of this would be
reusability. You create a nice
algorithm, some complex code, and
then you can save it as a view
and you have that reusability
factor. This business challenge
looks like a lot, but this covers
all of the topics that we will
be going over related to views.
Kelly, a grumpy worker in DAIS,
all hypothetical, not real world,
wants information from the
database, but we don't trust this
particular Kelly and we would
like to encrypt that data.
In addition, we only want to
provide Kelly access to the
student table via a view, so we
only want him to use the view.
We don't provide him access to
the student table, just access to
the viewed. Now that particular
writing of the access is kind
of behind the scenes. It's more
of a data administration language
code, so it's more the database
administration, but we can go in
and just provide Kelly with
access to views and not to tables.
We also don't want anybody
deleting columns while we're
using this view. And if
you think about referential
integrity, the idea is you
have to delete the child table
before you can delete the
parent table. Schema binding,
if I were making a flashcard,
is very similar to that.
Encrypt the view with encryption.
We've talked about that already
briefly. And then the third item is
we don't want Kelly inserting rows,
inserting information that's not
related to his area of access.
And we'll figure out what his
area of access is, and that's
using what's called the check
option. So that's everything
else we'll cover, encryption,
schema binding, and with the check
option, and then we'll go ahead
and conclude with the views.
So the first one is let's tackle
that encryption, create view,
and then I put this as VE
instead of first, and then with
encryption, notice that's before
the as because it's describing being
the view itself and then we have
the rest of the information.
So let me go ahead and
copy this. I'm going to go
back to our SQL Server and
the first thing I'm going
to do is I'm going to
create our original view.
All right, we have that view created
and I haven't created this view
yet but let's go ahead and refresh
again and take a look. we have
this view. If I right-click on this
view and I look at the design,
you can see that it has all of the
information, including the code,
the columns, the table structure
that we use to create this view.
Wow.
And also, I can write
this code. I think I had
it on the other slide.
SP underscore help text.
And then we'll call it. And
in that case it gives us
everything how we created the
view yikes and so let's go
ahead and run the second one
with encryption and again we put
a ve to describe encryption as
everything else is the same it's ve
first so it should run it looks like
it ran okay we're going to refresh
that but now look at the difference
our v first looks fine like a
normal pages you'll notice there's
a little lock on the encrypted
one. And the design is grayed out.
And then if we go and take a look
at that sp underscore help text and
we run that, nope, you can't have
access to it. So what we've done
is we've created some protection
around this view and only certain
people can access it. Next, let's
look at schema binding. And I think
earlier I mentioned we generally don't
use DBO database object. I forgot
before looking at this slide that
in order to do schema binding you
do have to do the two-part format
so you would have to include dbo
.student. The idea of schema binding
again is if we create this view we
don't want any of the underlying
tables to be deleted dropped because
then our view is no longer usable.
I don't know if there's a convention
for naming but I do have this one
as V, S, S for schema binding,
E for encryption.
Each company's gonna have
its own way to represent
code. So we have with encryption.
Also, before I forget,
you can use encryption and
schema binding together, and you
would do that just with a comma
and then writing encryption.
So just like you only have one order by,
you would only have one with as well.
So we could do that, but for
this we're just looking at
the schema binding. This is
very complex code. Select first
and last name from student,
but if I type in now drop
table
Student
In this case
We can't do it, but I think it's in
here. It's referenced by a foreign key
But if we ran a child table, we would
get the same kind of error message
So effectively it would do the same
you can't delete the underlying
table with that also as a
reminder This is because I forgot
about it from last semester,
but if I call this vfirst2 and
I don't have the full database
object, it needs the entire dbo
.student, so the entire naming
convention or the entire schema
for that particular object. And
the third one is check option.
And as you look at the
page, you'll notice that we
have a create view, vc,
vc for check option first.
And in this particular case, we've
got a little bit more complex code.
we have we have the check option
now if you think about when we did
encryption it was at the top when
we did schema binding it was also at
the top you'll notice that check
option is down below and let's copy
this and then i'll describe what the
check option does to show the delete
or some of the power of the check
option i've created a more simplified
view and the reason for that is
the other one had joins it gets a
little confusing when you start
trying to delete or change things So
let's just create this simple one.
It's similar to what we're giving
Kelly access to. It just has access
to building A. If we run this view,
select everything from
VCSimple, and this is perfect.
Okay, let me go ahead and
add an insert statement.
insert into.
All right, so here's the code we're going
to try to use using
the view. Insert into.
We have the three columns. We
don't use the first column,
which was, I think, locker number.
That's a surrogate key, but
we have this information.
Remember, we do have Kelly limited
through the check option, and
we run this code. It says,
the target view is a no-go with
the check option. Heck yeah.
And so he goes, fine,
okay, we'll put you in
building A. And you can do
this with insert, delete.
So go into building A.
And away we go. What a
cool thing. Check option.
It limits Kelly, the
fictional character Kelly.
All right, we'll finish up
with just a quick new topic. It
won't take long at all. The
top filter. Sometimes you just
want to limit the percentages
or the number of rows that
will return in your query, and
you can do that just through
the top option. I'll just show
you the two possibilities.
You could have, for instance,
select top five, and then
we'll just put everything,
but you could put specific
rows from student.
Now if you run this,
we get the top five.
Using top five, though,
technically, SQL grabs these
rows in whatever order they
choose to run it in. So in
most cases, you're going to
use select with an order by and
whatever that order by might
be. So we could do it by
last name in ascending order.
So most of the time, they go
hand in hand. And we can also use
either top five as a number or
you could use a percent. So in
this case, let's say top 50 and
then write the word percent.
and I checked my student number.
I thought I had an error. 81 rows,
so top 50% should give us, 80 should
give us about half of that. So
in this case, it delivers 41 rows
of data using the top function.
So that covers the views.
You've learned a lot about what
they are, how to build them,
how to get rid of them,
the encryption, the schema
binding, and the check option,
and we will see you in the next video to
cover case expressions. Have a great day.